H. Merle Cochran papers, 1922-1970
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
H. Merle Cochran papers, 1922-1970
MS 409
H. Merle Cochran
Papers, 1922-1970. This collection contains the papers of H. Merle Cochran. The bulk of the material is comprised of documents relating to Cochran's professional activities, including: his various posts in the U.S. Foreign Service (1914-1953), his role as deputy managing director of the International Monetary Fund (1953-1962), and his service as chairman of the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (O.E.C.D.) Consortium for Greece. Also included in the collection are photographs, mostly depicting official travel and social activities from the span of Cochran's career.
11 Linear Feet (Approximately 9,000 items)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None
Biographical Note
1892 Horace Merle Cochran born in Crawfordsville, Indiana
1913 B.S. University of Arizona
1914 M.S. University of Arizona
1914 Vice Consul; Mannheim, Germany
1914-1916 Vice Consul; Nogales, Mexico
1916 Vice Consul; Guatemala
1918-1919 Vice Consul; Luagno, Switzerland
1919 Vice Consul; Kingston, Jamaica
1920 Vice Consul; Port au Prince, Haiti
1920-1923 Vice Consul; Montreal, Canada
1923-1927 Deputy Liaison Officer; Washington (Department of State)
1927-1930 Consul; Paris, France
1930-1932 Consul; Basle, Switzerland
1932-1939 Financial Secretary of the Embassy; Paris, France
1939-1941 Technical Assistant to Secretary of Treasury; Washington (Department of State)
1941 Special Mission to China, (Stabilization Fund)
1941-1948 Senior Foreign Service Inspector
1949 U.S. Ambassador to Pakistan
1949-1953 U.S. Ambassador to Indonesia
1953 Retired from U.S. Foreign Service
1953-1962 Deputy Managing Director; International Monetary Fund
1963-1969 Chairman of Consortium for Greece; Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (O.E.C.D.)
Organization
This collection is organized into six series. Three of the series contain subseries.
Series I: Personal Files, 1934-1970
Series II: Foreign Service Files, 1927-1954
Subseries: Correspondence, 1931-1953
Subseries: Dispatches, 1929-1931
Subseries: Miscellaneous, 1927-1939
Subseries: Reports, 1927-1954
Subseries: Travel Files, 1930-1941
Series III: International Monetary Fund Files, 1952-1963
Subseries: Chronological Files, 1953-1962
Subseries: Correspondence, 1953-1963
Subseries: Miscellaneous, 1952-1959
Series IV: Organisation for the Economic Co-operation and Development Consortium for Greece Files, 1962-1969
Subseries: Chronological Files, 1963-1968
Subseries: Diaries, 1963-1969
Subseries: Miscellaneous, 1963
Subseries: Reports, 1962-1967
Series V: Photographs, 1930-1955
Series VI: Oversized Materials. 1922-1950
Scope and Content Note
This collection is composed of the papers of H. Merle Cochran, primarily including records from his work for three agencies: the U. S. Department of State (1927-1954), the International Monetary Fund (1954-1962), and the Organisation for the Economic Co-operation and Development (1962-1969).
Foreign Service Files contain material primarily pertaining to Cochran's role as a U.S. State Department Consular and Financial Secretary in Europe from 1927-1941, where he was assigned to report on international finance and banking. These activities are documented through Cochran's dispatches to the U.S. Department of State, correspondence, and reports (both his own and those compiled from various financial agencies). Travel files include meeting agendas, travel details, conference notes, and trip-related correspondence.
Most series contain some non-English language documents, particularly the Foreign Service Files, which contain materials in French, Swiss, and German, among other languages.
H. Merle Cochran's later administrative positions as Deputy Managing Director of the International Monetary Fund and Chairman of the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (O.E.C.D.) Consortium for Greece are documented extensively through correspondence, diaries, and chronological files comprised of mixed materials: primarily speeches, memoranda, minutes, correspondence, and notes.
Access Terms
Cochran, H. Merle.
Bank for International Settlements.
Diplomatic and consular service, American.
Economics -- Addresses, essays, lectures.
Economics -- Greece -- History.
International Monetary Fund.
Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development.
Container List
- Series I: Personal Files, 1934-1970
  .5 Linear Feet (Approximately 500 items)
  Arrangement: Alphabetical
  Personal Files contain biographical materials on the career and personal life of H. Merle Cochran, including correspondence, new clippings (from both Indonesian and English-language publications), biographical information, financial information, and his State Department Record of Service. The "Family History" folder contains materials collected on H. Merle Cochran's father--Lew Cochran--in addition to a Cochran family tree.
  - Biographical Information. 1951-1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence (A-G). 1953-1963 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence (H-R). 1949-1963 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence (S-Z). 1953-1970 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Family History. 1934-1939, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - News Clippings--International. 1948-1955 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - News Clippings--United States. 1939-1957 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Record of Service--U.S. State Department. 1953 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Tax Returns. 1957-1961 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Series II: Foreign Service Files, 1927-1954
  5.5 Linear Feet (Approximately 5,500 items)
  Foreign Service Files contain material from H. Merle Cochran's tenure as a Foreign Service officer, primarily relating to his consular service in Europe as a financial observer and reporter for the State Department between 1927 and 1941.
  The Foreign Service Files Series is divided into five subseries:
  Correspondence (1931-1953) contains correspondence of a general nature regarding Cochran's appointments and travels, as well as specific correspondence regarding the League of Nations Commission for the Study of International Loan Contracts (1937).
  Dispatches (1929-1939) contains those writings and materials dispatched directly from H. Merle Cochran at the U.S. Embassies in Basle and Paris to the U.S. Department of State in Washington D.C.
  Miscellaneous (1927-1939) contains a State Department manual for Foreign Service officers and a small number of publications regarding the Bank for International Settlements.
  Reports (1927-1954) contains various reports either written or compiled by H. Merle Cochran, supporting his research on international finance and economic trends. Of note are World War II era pamphlets and publications from various countries in the British Commonwealth, found attached to Cochran's extensive report on American-British Relations (circa 1942).
  Travel Files (1930-1941) contains correspondence, travel arrangements, and meeting and conference materials pertaining to Cochran's State Department trips.
  - Subseries:Correspondence
    - Committee for the Study of International Loan Contracts. 1937 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - General. 1931-1949 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - General. 1950-1953 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Subseries:Dispatches
    - Bank for International Settlements 1930-1939 (Box 1, Folder 13-20)
    - Foreign Bond Notes 1934 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - German Reparations. 1929-1930 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - International Bank Notes, # 1-19. 1931 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - International Bank Notes, # 20-39. 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - International Bank Notes, # 40-55. 1932 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - International Bank Notes, # 56-73. 1932 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - International Bank Notes, # 74-88. 1933 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - International Bank Notes, # 89-109. 1933 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - International Bank Notes, # 110-134. 1933-1934 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - International Bank Notes, # 135-154. 1934-1935 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - International Bank Notes, # 155-171. 1935-1936 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - International Bank Notes, # 172-203. 1936-1937 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - International Bank Notes, # 204-225. 1937 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - International Bank Notes, # 226-247. 1938 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - International Bank Notes, # 248-276 1938 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - International Bank Notes, # 276-297. 1939 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - International Bank Notes, # 298-299. 1939 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - International Loan Contracts. 1937 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - International Loan Contracts. 1938 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - International Loan Contracts. 1939 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Subseries:Miscellaneous
    - Bank for International Settlements--Press. 1930-1931 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Bank for International Settlements--Administrative History. 1932-1939 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - "Instructions to Diplomatic Officers." 1927 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Subseries:Reports
    - American-British Relations circa 1942 (Box 3, Folder 9-18)
    - American-British Relations circa 1942 (Box 4, Folder 1-5)
    - Bank for International Settlements--Annual Meetings. 1931-1954 (Box 4, Folder 6-7)
    - Bank for International Settlements--Capital Movements. DATE (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Bank for International Settlements--Central Banks. 1932-1933 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Bank for International Settlements--General. DATE (Box 4, Folder 10-12)
    - Bank for International Settlements--German Reparations. 1931-1936 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Bank for International Settlements--International Monetary Fund Development. 1944-1945 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Bank for International Settlements--Shares. 1934-1935 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - China Federal Reserve Bank. 1938 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Committee for the Study of International Loan Contracts. 1936-1937 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - German Debt Conference. 1934 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Gold Standard. 1930-1934 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
    - Income Tax Obligations under American Law. undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Japanese Financial Situation. circa 1939 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Lausanne Conference. 1932 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - League of Nations--Economic Conferences. 1927-1933 (Box 5, Folder 6-7)
    - Paris Bourse. 1930 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - "Problems of International Financing." 1936 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Saar Territory. 1935 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Settlement of the Turkish Debt. 1927-1928 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Silver Standard. 1932-1934 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Subseries:Travel Files
    - China--Exchange Stabilization Fund. 1941 (Box 5, Folder 13-17)
    - New York--Meeting of the Academy of Political Science. 1930 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - New York--Meeting of the Academy of Political Science. 1932 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Geneva--League of Nations. 1932 (Box 5, Folder 20-22)
    - Geneva--League of Nations. 1933 (Box 5, Folder 23-25)
    - Geneva--League of Nations. 1933 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Geneva--League of Nations. 1937 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - London-League of Nations. 1933 (Box 6, Folder 3-7)
    - New York--Bankers Forum. 1930 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Series III: International Monetary Fund Files 1952-1963
  1.5 Linear Feet (Approximately 1,500 items)
  The International Monetary Fund Files contain materials relating to H. Merle Cochran's nine year tenure as Deputy Managing Director of the Fund. The International Monetary Fund Files are divided into three subseries:
  Chronological Files (1953-1962) are composed of mixed materials pertaining to Cochran's role as Deputy Managing Director of the International Monetary Fund, including: correspondence, meeting minutes, speeches, financial reports, and travel information.
  Correspondence (1953-1963) contains official correspondence between H. Merle Cochran and the two managing directors he reported to while at the International Monetary Fund: Per Jacobsson and Rooth Ivar.
  Miscellaneous (1952-1929) contains internal publications and policies produced by the International Monetary Fund.
  - Subseries:Chronological Files
    - 1953. 1953 (Box 6, Folder 9-10)
    - 1954. 1954 (Box 6, Folder 11-12)
    - 1955. 1955 (Box 6, Folder 13-14)
    - 1956. 1956 (Box 6, Folder 15-16)
    - 1957. 1957 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - 1958. 1958 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - 1959. 1959 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - 1960. 1960 (Box 7, Folder 2-3)
    - 1961. 1961 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - 1962. 1962 (Box 7, Folder 5-7)
  - Subseries:Correspondence
    - Jacobsson, Per. 1954-1956 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Jacobsson, Per. 1957-1963 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Rooth, Ivar. 1953-1955 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Subseries:Miscellaneous
    - Articles of Agreement and Application for Membership. 1952-1959 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Audit Requirements. undated (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Policy on Exchange Restrictions. 1953 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Use of Fund Resources. 1953 (Box 7, Folder 14)
- Series IV: Organisation for the Economic Co-operation and Development Consortium for Greece Files, 1962-1969
  The Organisation for the Economic Co-operation and Development (O.E.C.D.) Consortium for Greece Files document Chairman H. Merle Cochran's effort to foster the economic development of Greece through bilateral negotiations with the Greek government and international agencies, as well as the solicitation of pledges of credit from O.E.C.D. member countries. The O.E.C.D. Consortium for Greece Files are divided into four subseries:
  Chronological Files (1963-1968) contain mixed materials reflecting the activities of the consortium, including: meeting minutes, memoranda, research materials, reports, speeches, and notes.
  Diaries (1963-1969) contain H. Merle Cochran's daily agendas and recollections of meetings, travel, and other events, reflecting his professional activities as chairman of the Consortium for Greece.
  Miscellaneous (1963) contains a publication of the regulations, rules and instructions for O.E.C.D. employees.
  Reports (1962-1967) contain compiled financial reports and other research materials regarding the Greek economic situation.
  - Subseries:Chronological Files
    - 1963. 1963 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - 1964. 1964 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - 1965. 1965 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - 1966-1967. 1966-1967 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - 1968. 1968 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Subseries:Diaries
    - 1963. 1963 (Box 7, Folder 20-22)
    - 1964. 1964 (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - 1965. 1965 (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
    - 1966. 1966 (Box 8, Folder 3-4)
    - 1967. 1967 (Box 8, Folder 5-6)
    - 1968. 1968 (Box 8, Folder 7-9)
    - 1969. 1969 (Box 8, Folder 10-12)
  - Subseries:Miscellaneous
    - Regulations, Rules, and Instructions (O.E.C.D.). 1963 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Subseries:Reports
    - 1962-1963. 1962-1963 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - 1964-1965. 1964-1965 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - 1966. 1966 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - 1967. 1967 (Box 8, Folder 17)
- Series V: Photographs, 1930-1955
  The Photographs Series contains photographs from throughout H. Merle Cochran's career, with the bulk of the material documenting his professional travel, meetings, and social engagements: first as a foreign service officer in Europe, then as the first United States Ambassador to Indonesia, and later, as a representative of the International Monetary Fund. Of note are the photographs documenting Eleanor Roosevelt's 1952 visit to Indonesia.
  - Asian Trip. 1955 (Box 8, Folder 18-21)
  - Bank of Holland. undated (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Cochran, H. Merle. undated (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Indonesia--Eleanor Roosevelt, Official Visit. 1952 (Box 8, Folder 24-25)
  - Indonesia--General. 1949-1953 (Box 9, Folder 1-6)
  - Miscellaneous--Assemblies. circa 1930s, 1940s (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous--Assemblies. circa 1950s, 1960s (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous--Buildings. undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous--Meetings. undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous--Social. undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous--Travel. undated (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Personal. undated (Box 9, Folder 13-15)
  - Portraits. 1921-1951 (Box 9, Folder 16-17)
  - University of Arizona--Commencement. 1962 (Box 9, Folder 18)
- Series VI: Oversized Materials, 1922-1953
  The Oversized Items Series contains certificates, diplomas, and awards received by H. Merle Cochran, Indonesian newspapers containing cartoons editorializing Cochran, and group and individual portraits from throughout his professional career.
  - Certificates--Department of State. 1938, 1944 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Certificates--French. 1927 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Certificates--Presidential. 1922, 1932, 1949 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Diplomas and Awards--University of Arizona. 1909-1949 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Newsclippings--Indonesian. 1949-1951 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Photographs--Group Portrait (Foreign Service Persons). 1933 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Photographs--International Monetary Fund. 1953-1962 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Photographs--Portraits. 1937-1938, undated (Box 10, Folder 8)